{
  "reference_number": "11686",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": "Remove the target from risk of political influence, instead and independent body is best - especially to respond to new research, and\n rapid changes in economics, and climate science, nationally and internationally"
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "Because the options are all 'net' rather than 'gross', we need to offset the impact of actual emissions. The 'net' measurement should\n\n be made on science of impact on climate change"
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "Once we have reached net emissions, we should then allow for trading, but not before - this would put NZ at a competitive advantage\n in the market."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, but the goal and underlying principle and purpose must be protected. As new research and new science is undertaken, of\n course we will need to have the ability respond - but this should be de-politicizied, and be the charge of a climate commission."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "That sounds reasonable - basically you need about this level of stability to have a predicable economic basis for investment. OR the\n independent climate commission could set the budget on a quarterly basis like the Reserve Bank does with the OCR. That level of\n\n control seems to keep most people happy."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "The government shouldn't be allowed to change the budget - the climate commission should be able however, to in the same way\n as the Reserve Bank is in control of the OCR - but with a different set of success criteria being monitored."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "No, if there are exceptional circumstances, they just need to make up for the short fall once the circumstances are no longer\nexceptional. The Government don't get to change the OCR in exceptional circumstances as much as they would like to. When faced\n\nwith exceptional economic circumstances the Government borrows money - and then they have to pay it back - that's the nature of a\nbalanced system, just as is required to mitigate climate change - we need to work within the ecosystem."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "However, these factors should be considered in terms of how they might impact NZ's ability to reduce or offset emissions, and\nshould not be considered in-and-of-there-own-right: - economic circumstances and, in particular, the likely impact of the decision on\n\nthe economy and the competitiveness of particular sectors of the economy • fiscal circumstances and, in particular, the likely impact\nof the decision on taxation, public spending and public borrowing • social circumstances and, in particular, the likely impact of the\n\ndecision on fuel poverty • energy policy and, in particular, the likely impact of the decision on energy supplies and the carbon and\nenergy intensity of the economy"
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Absolutely - the election conversation needs to shift from parties campaigning on 'if' they will act on climate change, to parties\ncampaigning on 'what' they will do to act on climate change."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Other environmental impact - e.g. what kind of trees are being planted? are these monocultures? Or diverse ecosystems that are\n\nbeing planted? Social Wellbeing Whole of life impact of projects/actions Iwi If two actions have the same emissions reduction/trade-off\n- then consideration on greatest benefit for economy, employment, and ROI"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I think greater emphasis on climate scientist expertise is required - do you need an atmospheric chemist for example? That seems\nlike a key area of expertise required to keep up with research in this area. Engineering and technologist expertise is required also -\n\nthere will be many technologies the commission will need to review and consider - and many sham technology solutions that will\nneed to be discounted."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "NO, that is a different set of actions that should happen in parallel and concert, but adaptation is a local concern, climate change\n\naction has a global impact."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes these are important - but I believe they should be decoupled from the core goal to reduce emissions, rather than conflated. This\nfeels like a different bill required on Adaptation"
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Sure, but this feels like a different bill required on Adaptation."
    }
  ]
}
